Rajat Talesra

in Rajat Talesra

O @rt4914

rajattalesra4914@gmail.com **□** rajattalesra.netlify.app **③**

Seasoned **Full-Stack** and **Mobile Developer** with over **8 years** of experience in leading diverse software projects. Proficient in Full-Stack development and **open-source initiatives**, with a strong track record in **project management** and **team leadership**.

Work Experience

Forem (dev.to) Nov 2023 - Jul 2021

Senior Software Engineer

- Led the development of an **Android app and library** called **Forem** achieving over **50K downloads** and maintaining a **4.5 average rating** on the Play Store.
- Implemented features enhancing user engagement through a **React**-based interactive dashboard, utilizing **Ruby on Rails** for backend processing, significantly improving admin and user experience and platform interactivity.
- Mentored new developers and managed community contributions, overseeing pull request reviews to maintain high standards of code quality and consistency.

Google (oppia.org) Jul 2021 - Jul 2019

Application Engineer

- Spearheaded Oppia-Android project from inception, achieving over 100K downloads in beta launch.
- Managed cross-functional international teams, focusing on architecture and documentation.
- Led Core Learning and Mastery team and onboarding team.
- Ensured full accessibility for non-sighted users.
- Continued mentoring in GSoC for three years post-contract.

Keycard Technologies

Jul 2021 - May 2016

Founder | Director

- Founded company to develop and enhance **facial recognition attendance** system with 22 other features, successfully adopted in schools.
- Received INR 10 Lakh government grant for technological innovation.
- Led projects in e-commerce and jewellery sectors, overseeing technology, sales, and marketing.

Projects

Youtube Channel Present - Jan 2024

- Creating videos on Ruby on Rails, React, Android and everything in between.
- · Ruby on Rails airbnb clone series.
- React + Rails API Series

Zerg Gaming app Jan 2021 - Mar 2020

- Led the development of a Android gaming platform, managing the project lifecycle and team.
- Launched alpha app with 5 single-player games and 2 multi-player games like Ludo and Poker.
- Project explanation video.

Numrah Jun 2020 - Dec 2019

• Developed Chitter, an anonymous chat Android app, specializing in web-sockets for real-time communication.

Android Tutor Jan 2017- Mar 2015

• Mentored and taught android app development course to **2500+ students** in 15+ universities across India in collaboration with **Google, IEEE and Udacity**.

• Featured on Google Student Blog.

Skills

Frontend: HTML, CSS, JavaScript, React, TailwindCSS

Fullstack: Ruby on Rails
Mobile: Android, Kotlin, Java
Databases: PostgreSQL, Firebase
Other: Git, Github, Figma, Accessibility

Education

DAIICT, Gandhinagar, India

B.Tech. Information and Communication Technology

July 2012 - May 2016